so today last lesson um yeah i'm smiling but i'm sad uh
i wanted to talk about energy-based models and how to train them
but i think i need to prepare like for a month before that
so actually uh if you are still interested in this summer you will be
able to get a tutorial on energy-based models uh
we are writing a paper with jan together and so we actually i'm
planning to get this paper written as like part it's going to be math and then
part is going to be actually the implementation
such that you can actually execute uh the paper basically and you can get you
know a better understanding of what's going
on um yeah so yeah that's gonna come out maybe
in a month uh we we i have to do pretty a pretty good
job there um so and maybe uh if the
maybe we can even have a additional class later on
if you're interested and you know i'm always here uh
up for uh teaching you so again if you're interested in this energy-based
model later on like outside the course and whatever we
can again meet and uh record and and pretend it's
actually one more class okay so yeah i i didn't
manage to do it for today so today we're going to be covering um
if i get to finish two topics um we never
talked about them uh too much before uh because they are more machine learning
related but nevertheless we care also in deep learning and the
topic of today is regularization overfitting and
regularization let me start sharing the screen so again this is my
as usual perspective of the topic uh it's not usually the
mainstream but you know it's what you get since it's my
view and i'm your educator your instructor today
so overfitting and regularization connection between them right so
those are two different topics those are two different things but they are of
course connected so i start with this drawing
here uh someone told me it's not intuitive
but again for me so there you get it
uh here i'm showing you in the uh with the pink box the data complexity
okay so those dots are sampled from my
samples from from my training data set and
then i tried to fit their three different models okay
so in the first case that is basically the model complexity is below
is under is you know it's smaller than the data
complexity and therefore you have some phenomenon
called under fitting right because you try to fit
uh what looks like a parabola with a straight line and therefore you're
not you're not going you're not doing a good job right
then what happened next here we actually have the right fitting
in this case the model complexity matches
the data complexity right um and so in this case what's the difference with
the previous case uh in this case you have zero error right
so your your model exactly matches the training
points those points finally we have overfitting where
the model complexity is actually
greater than the data complexity in this case
the model doesn't choose a parabola because why question for your
audience live my own live audience why is this model like
wiggly in this case why is not a parabola
and you're supposed to type in the chat because otherwise
i don't know if you're following so my question is in
the last case my data my model complexity is superior than the
it's larger than the data complexity and although those points look like they
belong to a parabola my model decides to get that spiky guy
like spiky peak on the left and you know some weird stuff
model doesn't learn but memorizes um overfitting but sure sure it's written
they're overfitting but why if those points are coming from a
parabola i would expect even a very larger model
would make like a very nice parabola right
you're privately writing to me don't private
private right um so if
and this is a big if right if my points my training points come from
an actual parabola even the overfitting model would be making a perfect parabola
the point here is that there is some noise
right there is always some noise and therefore the model that perfectly
goes through every training point will be like that it's going to be like
crazy because all those points don't exactly live on
the parabola but they are slightly offset and in order to be
perfectly uh going through them you're gonna have
you know the mother is gonna have to try to
come up with some funky function okay does it make sense
so the point is that without noise this would be just a perfect parabola
so someone would say okay maybe we should use the right fitting right
in machine learning maybe we are doing deep learning
and it's not quite the case right fitting
it's it's definitely not the case actually our models
are so so so so powerful that they even managed to learn noise like there
was a paper there where they were showing that you can
label ImageNet with random labels you can get a network
to you know perfectly memorize every label
uh for each of these samples so you can
clearly tell that these the models we are using
are absolutely over parameterized and therefore means that
you have way more power than the uh you know then then it's necessary
in order to learn the structure of the data nevertheless
we actually need that hmm so let's figure out what's going on okay
um oh actually maybe you know the answer
right so what is the point why do we want to go in very very high
dimensional space i told you a few times right because
who answers come on it's the last class answer me
why do we want to go in very to expand the
the data distribution yeah optimization is easier yeah fantastic
that's the point right whenever we go in a hype over parameterized space
everything is very easy to move around right and therefore we always
would like to put ourselves in the overfitting
scenarios with our networks because it's the training is going to be easier
nevertheless what's the problem now well the problem is they
they're going to be like they wiggle like crazy
um another another thing um so this is point number one point number
two why would you think you actually
have to overfit when writing your script
second question i know interactive question today
actually sure there is some trend you can model okay maybe
maybe it's in the right direction but it's too complicated as an answer
um so are you experts you're a network trainer you should be
right because you've been following these lessons for a bit but um
at the beginning okay try to answer this question
so why would you like to overfit i even tell you one one bit more i would
always i do always start training my network on
one batch if the model has capabilities so this is
the number one rule to debug machine learning code okay
you would like to see whether you [ __ ] up in your
model creation okay so first thing you can just get a batch of the correct
size uh even with random noise right even you
know torch dot trend something with random
labels and then you would like to go over a few
epochs with one batch with random crap which could be the
first batch of your data set or whatever just to prove that your model can learn
okay you can easily make some tiny mistakes
uh like i made a few times like doing the
zero zero grad uh after the backward
yeah i know it happens and nothing happens nothing learns okay so you
always want to see that your model model can learn right
then if you can memorize yeah fantastic we are
going to be now learning how to uh improve performance of a model that
memorizes uh its own data okay so two reasons
right first one we said over parameterize
uh models are easy to train because the landscape is much smoother
us and you know if you have a over parameterized model you're gonna
have you can uh ideally start with different
initializations so you get initial points in the parameter space and then
whenever you train these different models all of them will
converge to a different position because you can
think about like a same model you can permute all the weights you're gonna get
i mean you permeate the weights per layer
you can still get the same uh model at the end so they are comparable in
terms of the function approximator you are building nevertheless in the
parameter space they are not the same right so in the function
space they are exactly equivalent models in the parameter space they are
absolutely different models nevertheless they will converge to
equivalently equivalent models as in they will
perform equivalently equivalently good right are you following right am i
talking about weird stuff today but uh i guess this counts a bit also from
Joan’s class where we talk about parameter space and
functional uh functional space it's so so cool in
that class i think next year i will try to put it online as well okay
okay so first point over pardon me over
parameterization helps with training second point or over parameterization
helps you with math debugging can you repeat the point
about function and parameter space yeah so if you have a neural net and you
permute the rows in your matrices right and then you
permute the uh the column of the
uh the next layer you can basically you know you can reorganize the weight
so you can get always the same performance right
so if you have the first matrix you have first element of the hidden layer equal
some number let's say the hidden layer has size of
two right so you have a matrix with two rows
and so you can swap the the rows you're gonna get a hidden layer that is flipped
and then the last the next next weight matrix
you can flip the um columns i guess uh and you would get
exactly the same network the same you would sorry you would get exactly
the same function it's gonna give you exactly the same
number as an output although the parameters the the
parameters are actually different right because you swap them so
the same parameter w11 is going to be w21 right so they are
different so in the parameter space these are different models so there are
one point is here in the parameter space another point is here
nevertheless the mapping from the parameter space to the functional space
both of them both these two initial those two configuration
will map to the same function right because the
function connects the input to the output and they're going to be the same
even if you do this permutation of the rows and then and
of the columns right makes sense so if if we
if the space of parameters if the space for parameter space is very
big for a given data set can we say that the model is very uncertain about
its prediction okay we are going to be talking about uncertainty in a bit so
i'll address that in a bit all right so we always start with the
third uh column here with overfitting uh i
always want to have a model that is over parameterized because it's easy to learn
and also it's going to be powerful in terms
in the sense that it's going to be learning more than what we
expect um and so how do we deal with these overfitting
how do we improve now the validation or tasting
performances right so we we said that overfitting means uh we
didn't say we're gonna see that next slide but
here we see how to fight this kind of you know overfitting
so we start from the right hand side where we introduce
this weak regularizer so there is no regularization
therefore the last plot the sixth plot here
is the same as my third plot okay then i keep uh adding some
medium regularizer and so i i like to think about this as you know
smoothing edges right so my square gets around edges
and you can tell now that this second plot here is different from my second
window here right so the the medium regularization is different from
this just right fitting as you can see there are some you know
corners here finally if you crank up this medicine
this kind of you know it's like a drug you you're
drugging you're hitting you're poisoning your model for to restrict the
it's it's power then you get like a very strong regularizer
which gives you the the circular one that's this this is my
mental image anyhow we we gave you i think i give you my
uh the big picture first and then let's go on with the actual
definitions right um so there are a few definitions here
they are not quite equivalent but in deep learning that's what we use
so here we go so the regularization adds prior knowledge to a model a prior
distribution is specified for the parameters
so we expect these parameters to be coming from a specific distribution from
a specific generation generating process okay
and then whenever we actually think about regularization we can think about
you know uh strongly assuming that these parameters should be
um coming from this specific process that generates them okay so this
is talking about parameter space then we can also talk about the
functional space in this case we can be it can be seen a
regularization is a restriction of the set of possible learnable
functions okay so these are again two perspective one is on the weights
where how are supposed to be what kind of
weights what kind of animals what kind of objects
these weights are like they should be somehow over some specific shape
uh length or whatever structure there is there is some structure that
i assume uh in advance that's the prior this means before in
latin and in others in another case instead if you
have all possible function you'd like to find a restriction of
those possible functions such that they are not too
uh crazy okay they are not too extreme as in
the way they behave ah there's a question but in that image the
square is still in the circle uh
yeah i'm getting back oh oh i see so maybe the circle should
have been smaller than the square okay
right good point um okay cool cool finally that's the last definition of
regularization which is the real real deep learning part which is the
following which is yeah kind of not it's like you know
as a stretch okay my google thinks i'm talking
italian what the heck okay regularization is any modification
we make to a learning algorithm that is intended to reduce its generalization
error but not its training error okay so this is actually
a stretch because it's no longer talking about prior knowledge and
functional space but actually modification to learning
algorithms so this is like moving towards maybe programming you
know so parameters function then it's like
algorithmic implementation right so these are really three different
perspective of the same thing cool so first let's start with
regularizing regularizing techniques a few examples
so first actually i start with xavier initialization i told you before that we
can think about these parameters as coming from some generation generating
process right so whenever you initialize a network you
can choose to to you can choose to select one uh
regular um one prior right so these are this is defining where your um
your your weights are coming from so in this case we can choose xavier normal
which is a initialization technique and this assumes this kind of gaussian
gaussian distribution right so you have the weight space by weight values and
you know the most of them will be peaked towards the zero and then you have some
kind of um some some kind of
standard deviation that is based on the size of the input and output
size of that specific layer and so from here we can
start introducing the weight decay weight decay is the first regularization
technique that is widespread in machine learning
not be not maybe too much in neural nets
still relevant so weight decay uh you can find it in
directly inside the optim package like you it's a flag in
the the different in the different optimizer
is also called l2 regularization ridge regression or
gaussian prior which basically tells you that things
come from this gaussian process or gaussian you know distribution
generating distribution nevertheless we call it weight decay so
why do we call it weight decay uh so this is first thing that you know
if you train neural net you're going to call
weight decay not the other things so we can start with this Jtrain that's
our objective which is acting upon the parameters and
which is equal the old training the the one without the
regularization plus a penalty term like um like
the following so we have the the square norm
the square two norm right of these parameters
and so if you uh make the if you compute the
the gradient of course you're gonna get just the
λθ right because the two comes down simplifies you get that guy
so if you think about this um second equation
what you see you say that the θ gets previous θ minus you know the
the minus step so like minus a step towards uh the gradient
some a step towards the opposite direction of
the gradient such that you can go down the hill right in your training
laws minus some ηλ which is a
a scalar multiplying by θ right and that means that it's
going to be you know the first part there is you all go
down the hill whereas the other one tells you
and go also towards where zero right and so how does this how does
this look so this looks like this right in every
point so consider we are already trained and the
training loss is zero and we just consider the second term
right so let's consider we already finished training so
there is no there is not this term we just have theta
minus eta lambda theta what does it mean so if there is no uh at the first term
here in any point you are so in theta you're
going to be subtracting some multiplier some scalar you know i
told you scalar a scalar is what scales right
so this scalar scales this vector probably by a factor that is slower than
one and so if you're here this one is going to take you down on
the point that is connecting your head of the
theta towards zero right or this point here
this is θ and then it takes you down to zero okay
so if you don't have this term here and you perform a few steps
in this uh you know in this parameter update
you're gonna get that the vector field that you know results
is something that attracts you towards zero and that's why it's called weight
decay right so if you let it go this stuff too it's gonna decay to zero
makes sense right so these are very cute drawings
i think cool so okay now you know about weight decay a
weight decay is also we can think about this as adding a
constraint over the length of a vector so the
length of a vector is the you know the the the euclidean norm
and so here we basically try to reduce the length of this vector
so weight decay is a way to reduce the length
okay so l1 what is this l1 so l1 can also be
used as a flag in the optimizer in torch it's also called lasso which is least
absolute shrinking selector operator wow yeah statisticians whatever
it's also called a laplacian prior because it comes from a laplacian
probability distribution and then also it can be called as a
sparsity prior why is that so this is this is pretty interesting so here in
the bottom part you can see there is the dashed line uh
represent my gaussian prior right and then here i
just show you the laplace what's the difference with laplace laplace is the
same as gaussian so you have the exponential
but instead of having the quadratic square norm you have the
uh one norm okay and so the the whereas the the the
you know whereas the quadratic is very shallow like it's very flat
towards zero the the l1 is like a it's a spiky right so that's why if you
get the exponential you get like you get a spike this is
minus the the absolute value right so you get a
spike for the laplacian or you get like a smooth for this square
because you have the parabola right which is smooth on the
bottom part okay so the point is that there is much
more mass now in this region than
it was before right so this is pretty this is like a spike there is much more
probability that you get something towards zero nevertheless maybe this is
not too clear as an explanation so i show you
the second diagram so in this case my training loss instead of being the
all train loss i'm going to be summing λ
the norm 1 of my θ okay therefore if you compute the gradient of
the l1 what do you get l one is going to be
just one right if you're positive or it's going to be
minus one in the sine function yeah exactly
so you get η λ sin(θ) and so let's now think
the same way what happens uh if you already finished training you don't have
this term over here and you just get θ - η λ sin(θ)
so if you are on the on the x axis you know the the y
is completely doesn't have is is already zero so you're going to get some
arrows bringing you in right so if you're on the axis you're gonna get
exactly as l2 you're gonna go towards zero
now what happened if you're in first quadrant
so in the first quadrant you get a sign in both direction right scale by the
scalar factor there and so it's going to be pointing down
deeply so here i show you the uh the the gray arrows here
they're showing you the l2 regularization which are taking you
from the initial point towards zero is proportional to this vector that is
here whereas the l1 which is going to be in a
different color and color green the l1 instead
starting from here it takes you down 40 degrees here and then what happened
here well you just kill the y component right
and so the l1 uh better feel
it will quickly kill components that are close to the axis
right so if you're kind of close to the axis this one bomb
takes you down to the axis in a view in a
few steps right and then if you still apply this one you're going to go down
the axis here right so this one allow you to
quickly go down here and then if you still apply you can shrink the length
but the point is that you're not looking at the
length shrinking as in the in in the l2 right so l2 was just
shrinking the length of the vector in the l1 instead you actually gonna
kill the components that are kind of cl
near the axis okay so i think you can clearly now understand how this
works right so uh and this actually is quite relevant
for training let's say you know our regularized
regularized latent variable models because you can you know you can think
about you know a very quick way to regularize this this
latent virus is going to be just killing some of these components such
that only the information is going to be restricted in a few of these
values okay you like this stuff you like the drawings
no they're cute i think okay uh okay drop out right so we we talk i
think about dropout a few times but i never show you
the animation so boom okay so dropout what does this
dropout do so i can show you my ninja skills in
powerpoint and we have an infinite loop animation
so the input in the pink is provided to the network
uh and then you have that these hidden layers hidden
neurons are sometimes set to zero in this case is you have a dropping rate
of 0.5 so half of the neurons are gonna be turned
to zero on uh randomly during the training
and so what happens here is that there is
no more path between the input and the output
that is uh you know there is no learning of a singular path for input to
output so every time if you want to try to
memorize one specific input you can't because every
time you get a different network and so again this basically tell you
uh oh scarf okay so what happens here is that again
before if we have like a fully connected network like this
you can think about oh i won't like to memorize this
neuron uh going this path and then here right so you can try to
memorize uh some specific you know sample you get
you can memorize a specific sample in this case but again if you have the net
product that is taking off neurons sometimes sometimes
this neuron here on the left hand side doesn't exist
right and so if this one doesn't exist
then you cannot memorize a specific path moreover you can think about this
dropout as training a infinitely infinite
number of networks that are different right because every time you you drop
some neurons you basically get a new network
uh they all share the initial kind of starting position with the initial
weights but then at the end whenever you use it
i inference usually you turn off this dropout
and then you have to scale the the weights right because otherwise you get
a network that is you know blowing you up this is because if you
have half of the neurons off you know the other neurons are doing
the half of the neurons are doing the whole job and if you turn everyone
on you're going to have twice as many more
uh values so so you can do two things or when you actually use dropout you
crank up you multiply by by let's say one over uh the dropping
rate so if you have dropping rate of 0.5 you can multiply by two such that
uh your neurons are twice as powerful right
twice is more powerful uh than one minus 0.5 right one divided one
minus 4.5 so if you have a dropping rate of 0.1
uh means you have 90 of your neurons there
and so your neuron should be one over 0.9
stronger right um to be to have like the same kind of
power right in terms of values anyhow so you can
think about uh drop dropout as having these multiple
networks during training but then whenever you use them at
inference you turn off this dropout module and you basically average out all
these performance of the singular network and
these allow you to get you know a much better
reduction of the noise uh which was introduced
like that was arised by the the training procedure
because again if you have you know multiple experts you take the average of
multiple experts you're going to get a better
um answer because it's going to be removing that kind of variability in the
specific answer right but perhaps we should keep in mind this
variability of the answers okay because it can turn out quite
interesting anyhow so dropout is amazing way to
basically have an automatic model averaging
modeling assembling performance cool cool cool uh is dropout a good
technique only for classification task or also
for other tasks as well like metric learning and coding learning
i would say that dropout gives you a much more robust
network a much more robust prediction regardless of the task it doesn't it
doesn't restrict to classification you basically train uh multiple networks
of reduced size right and then you average out this reduced size network
so although at the end you're going to have a large network this large network
is just the average of small networks performance
so and also if you think in this way the small network can no longer overfit
right because they are no longer that over parameterized
perhaps right and so dropout allows you allows you to
fight overfitting with several by different you know
mechanisms finally you can think uh if you apply
let's think about like uh applying dropout to the input
this is kind of uh sort of like uh denoising out encoder no i mean you
perturb the input right in in this case and then you force
still the output to be the same so if you think about that you are going
to be insensitive to some small variations of
the input uh which are gonna make your network
more robust right or the same as i was as i wrote you in
the midterm uh how can you get a input that is you
know annoying you can find some noise in the input
which is going to be increasing your uh your loss right so
you can do some kind of adversarial generation of noise and then you try to
you train your network on these um handcrafted samples which were
um corrected were like perturbed in order to
increase your your training loss right okay so i gave you like
four different reasons why to use dropout but then i don't use dropout
some not that often i actually do use it for a different reason which i'm going
to be coming to that in a bit um okay so early stopping so this is
much one of the most basic techniques uh if
you're training your model and your validation
loss starts starts increasing
then you stop there okay such that you get the lowest validation
score and which tells you okay you're not yet
overfitting uh and that basically doesn't let your
weights grow too much right so instead of
getting the l2 which is trying not to get those weights to get
too lengthy too long too long you just stop whenever they are
not yet that long right uh fighting overfitting so these are
techniques that end up regularizing our parameters our models but
but they are not they are not regularizers okay so this is important
these are not regularizer although they do regularize
the uh network okay as long as you keep this in mind we
can also see these uh other options but they are
not regularizing techniques right they do
act as a regularizer though first one batch
normalization okay so we talked about this several
times we don't know quite how it works too
well there is an article on a blog post that
is explaining this i we put the link in the optimization
lecture check it out i think it's like lecture
seven of some blog post i really can't remember anyhow
so the point is that you reset the the mu then the mean and
the sigma the the sigma square the variance
at each layer and these allow you to
okay when you reset the mean and the sigma this is based on the specific
batch you have right because you compute the mean and the sigma square
over the specific batch but then if you actually sample uniformly from your
training data set you will never have two identical batches right so every
batch will have a different configuration of samples therefore if
you compute the mean and the standard deviation they will always
be different right and therefore again i said five
times therefore you are going to be applying a different
correction per batch and the model will never see twice the
same input right because they are altered based on where they happen to
uh appear in your training uh procedure so because you never
showed the same uh same input twice and this is so cool uh i really like it
and that's all you need usually most of the time to train your network
don't drop out and this technique also speeds up your
training like crazy before batch norm was introduced
it was taking me i think one week to train uh
on ImageNet i think at least if it was if it wasn't a month it was
terrible i think but again that's like eight years ago uh
yeah it was terrible training on ImageNet uh with batch normalization i
think you can train in one day so that's ridiculous do you mean robust in
terms of adversarial learning as well i don't understand why we don't see the
same sample twice um i'm saying robust here
as in uh you're providing different inputs every time because and so the
network gets a better coverage what is the training
manifold uh you don't see the same input twice
because the same input based on how it appears in the in the
batch so if you appears you have you know input 42
and this input 42 happens in a given batch
you subtract the mean of the batch and divide by the standard deviation
and you get the the new you know value right within the network
but then if that input 42 happens in a different batch
then the mean of the different batch is gonna be a different mean
and therefore you're gonna get a slightly different
input every time so you never actually observe the same input because they
happen to be packed in a different batch and therefore the statistics of that
specific patch will be just specific to that batch and
you know it's going to change every time you're going to have a different batch
so same input get a different [Music]
correction let's say this way if it appears in a different batch so it
you never see the same input twice so this technique is all i use usually for
training my network um and it works but again recently i've
been using dropout for a different reason so we're gonna be
um okay we are gonna see this in a few minutes uh
more data of course just providing more data you're gonna find all over fitting
but then you know ding ding ding okay
uh finally data augmentation so data augmentation is also a very valid
technique in order to you know prove provide some kind of
uh deformed version of the input if you're talking about images we have
center crop color jitter different crops transformations like i find random
transformations crops random rotation horizontal flip
right if you see myself like that and you flip my face i'm still me kind of
right so uh if it's upside down well maybe not quite uh nevertheless you can
see that if you provide some alterations that are
perturbation that you are if you like to be insensitive against
then you can improve your performance of the network which is going to be
learning how to be insensitive to this kind of
uh you know variations okay okay okay so quickly quickly
quickly oh okay transfer learning we already know about transfer learning
i think but again so you get your network you already trained on a
specific task you just leave the first classifier there
you move everything you plug a new a new classifier or
whatever and then if you have you know a few data
with a similar kind of training distribution
you just do transfer learning which is again
training just the final classifier uh if you have lots of data
you should fine-tune because you would like to
also improve this uh the performance of the
like you would like also to tweak the uh feature extractor the blue
the blue layers and the colors are flipped here damn the hidden layer
should have been green and the output blue okay
few data and different from training or you want to do early
uh transfer learning which means you know you start
changing um also you know a little bit of the the of the other
layers as well not all of them and then
yeah you want to remove a few more layers actually yeah oh
my bad so you would like to remove a few of those uh
final hidden layers because they are kind of already specialized
so you want to retrain the base features extractor here
and if you have lots of data which are different from the training the
distribution just train okay um okay also you can use different
learnings learning rate for different layers right
to improve performance so maybe you um
you'd like to change um yeah so you you can you can see that usually
these final layers are the ones that are changing uh quicker because they are
close to the uh to the loss but then again if you use
uh batch norm all these layers are kind of training the same
speed otherwise again you can see whether you want to change learning rate
maybe change these guys slower or not did you say is
the difference between transfer learning and fine
tuning uh transfer learning i just train define a classifier
because i don't have if you have few data you don't have
enough you know you don't want to overfit so you
if you have a few data you want to just reuse the whole
network from the previous task and you just train the final classifier
if you have lots of data then you can actually even um
try to have like some changes you can also you know you can start
you have a uh lower learning rate you also change for
this feature extractor if they are similarly transfer learning you freeze
the the base network yeah i would say the transfer
learning you just freeze the the blue guy and you just
train the orange in uh fine tuning you actually tune
all the other parameters as well maybe with smaller learning rate
this is the number 12 notebook here i'm classifying the
sentiment of these reviews on the IMDB data set all right and so i'd like to
compare different regularization techniques
so i'm just keeping everything because i just like to show you the final result
let me see where is the optimizer so you can toggle different things at
the beginning we have no weight decay nothing right so we
train with this regularizer let's check what is the model so the
model is just a feed forward neural net which is fifo on neural net we have some
embeddings a linear a linear and then my forward is going to be
getting my embeddings sending to the forward the fully connected ReLU
uh and then you know you get the output from this so second fully connected and
i'm outputting a sigmoid because i'm just doing
um i think a two-class classification problem so we'd like to figure out if
it's a positive review or a negative review
um and so this is the initial training and we got you know
the validation curve climbs up as crazy whereas the training curve goes down to
zero and so here you can see uh the
validation accuracy which goes up to 64 more or less so and here we just
store the weight of the network
for when there is no kind of regularization okay
then first thing i'd like to do is going to be trying to do the
weight l1 the l1 regularization so let's see how to do that
so l1 regularization okay toggle this one to do
l1 regularization so here i'm extracting the
model parameters and then i'm going to be adding
some term to the to the loss okay so the loss is going to
be some part of this uh like i'm gonna sum the the one norm
of the fc1 to the loss okay because there is no other way to do this
in a PyTorch for the moment okay so let me re-initialize the network
so i start here [Music]
i get [Music]
this one and then i start training here so this guy is training uh how many
iterations let's check 10 epochs okay one two three
four five six all right so before we were checking
we can go down here we had the validation accuracy was around 64.
and now we have validation accuracy went to 66 right so we actually have
improved the performance by getting these guys
uh to be oh it's getting down down
oh back up 67 looks good 68 okay it's finished so i can show you in
this case what happened with l1 oh it's not yet finished okay it's
taking forever okay while this is training okay okay
i'm gonna show you the the output of this guy and then i'm gonna be
showing just briefly the uh second usage of the dropout should we
stop this guy 69 so you can see now here we are at 69
in validation at 30 right okay cool and here you can see both the
training and the validation they are both losses they go down and
then here i show you the validation which went up to 67 and 68 okay
and so here i just show i gonna be storing these weights
for the l1 so here i just store this l1 over here
okay i'm gonna go back here
uh we are gonna be undoing this one right because we don't
want uh l1 we're gonna be choosing now a l2 regularizer
right so i can toggle this one and toggle this on alright so now we
have a weight decay of this value
model i execute this one and i execute these guys all right
so while the l2 is training i'll just show you
a quick uh overview about bayesian neural nets
so estimating a predictive distribution so why to care about uncertainty many
reasons uh if you have a cat declassifier and
you show a hippopotamus the network is going to tell you oh this
is a dog no it doesn't know i cannot tell you oh
this is not of any of the above right you can think about oh let's make a
third category but then how can you show you how can
you show the network not a cat and not a dog uh it doesn't
quite work like that so you can't really find i mean cat is
an object dog is a object not a cat or not a dog
is not an object so you can't really train your network
to say everything else um reliability on steering control let's
say you're training your car to steer right and left
and then your car say steer to the right okay hold on
how certain are you about this action is it is it gonna kill me right
uh physics simulator prediction if you know about
physics or physicists they always want to know
how certain you are about your value right so measurements
uh in physics always have you know you have the value plus minus the
uncertainty so you know your network should be able
to tell you as well how certain uh some number or what is the
in the confidence interval for a specific prediction
moreover you can think to use this for minimizing action randomness when
connected to a reward what the heck does this mean
so if there is some uncertainty with some
associated some to some actions you can actually exploit that
and train your model to minimize that uncertainty and this is so cool because
we use something similar in my in our
project right so dropout i told you about before uh so
how this neural network dropout works i just gonna be quickly going through
this i multiply my input and my hidden layer with these random
zero one masks okay and you can have the activation function to
be some non-linearity and then here you have this bernoulli
with the probability of one minus the dropping out
rate so this the dropping out rate and then you want to scale
the delta such that you know you resize the amplitude
of those weights the training has just finished so i'm gonna be
switching that i'm sorry for the context switching
oh okay good call all right uh calculate the variance yes someone was
saying calculate the variance i know i'm switching i'm sorry it's the last lesson
i'm making a mess okay so this is train and we got 64 uh
which is so these are also going both down
this is both the the l2 regularization and before we were getting to 68 with
the l1 here we get something else maybe
oh you can see it's still climbing right so maybe i just stopped too early
so if you keep training you're gonna get a better performance
it's it's monotonic non-decreasing right so i think
kind of so i think you can squeeze more and here i'm gonna be saving
these weights in these l2 weights okay so i saved that and the last one
then i sh then it's gonna be exactly the dropout
right so go back here uh we turn off
the l2 so we turn off this guy we turn back the
simple one but then we have to go back in this
network we would like to turn on the dropout rate
true there you go boom boom boom okay is it training yeah it's training
all right cool cool cool back to the presentation
i i know i'm sorry i'm going over time what a bad teacher
okay so this is actually what we are doing the dropout part right
okay cool cool all right so this is my dropout
and i mean i mean i am basically multiplying these inputs and hidden
layers with masks here you just have like a network which
is trying is trying to train that you know uh
prediction uh that is weakly prediction is like a co2
concentration level uh if you use a gaussian kernel with a
square exponential kernel you can get you know
after the dashed line the network say that you
know the the model says i have no clue so i give you my prediction which is
zero but then this is my confidence level
can we do something similar with neural nets yes we can
so this is a uh uncertainty estimation we're using the
ReLU non-linearity in the network and this is instead
using tanh which is is actually nothing um if i'd like to do a binary
classification in the first case are gonna be my logic
uh on this section -3 to 2.5 is the
training training training interval and then
if i show you if i show my network uh if i ask oh what is the prediction for
x* if i don't use any uncertainty
estimation you're gonna get a very high value
right which is corresponding to oh this is uh
one so this is my one class if i just use the the
white big thick line instead if you use this uncertainty estimation
you get this network to get those logics here with it kind of
you know blur foggy shadow and therefore if you apply
the sigmoid you get basically that to flip down from zero to one right
so you no longer say it's one you can say
it's one with some specific probability right
um and here i'm showing you a network that is trying to it was trained on
ammunite and then you provide a one that is you
know tilting and then you can see that it begins with
having a high value for the logits for the purple for
the for the one and then as you move across
it becomes like a five and then becomes a seven
because it looks like some part of the one
like some part of the seven right and these are the output
after the uh soft arc max so you see that uh you know after you tilt they get
very blur and very spread around so how can we
have something like that and this is the other notebook
so we are done here with the regularization let me give you the final
thing so here we can see with the dropout you always have the validation
and train curves they are one on the other and
then this was the l2 regularization i can execute this
other one which shows you also that this is keep
increasing right so although the model is over parameterized we are not
overfitting which was the case uh at the beginning finally here let's
store these weights in the dropout version
okay so i save all of them uh and so i can start showing you a few
things um for example this one
let's see if it works boom so here you can see that the red
are the l1 and the red one are basically all
in the center bam and all the other reds are
to zero right so n1 i just show you the histogram of the weights
when i train the network with the l1 regularizer you get all of these are
here in the purple case you actually have
it looks like it's higher i'm not entirely sure
why you have a higher peak at zero in l2 but then the purple one have some values
as well here in the tails whereas if there is no regularization
you get something that is you know resembling a much
spread a much spread gaussian right so you get values that
are much much more much larger okay instead the l1
should be all towards you know very very short
again i'm not sure why this purple is taller than the the red here i think
it's an issue so this i i show you the the the weights
we can show lastly last individual one l1 so l1 all are here
and this is these are instead the one with nothing
right so these are the one without the regularization
and these are the one with the l1 regularization
we can also have more bins to have i bet a better understanding of what's going
[Music] on
okay see boom fantastic right i can show you also the weights
l2 l2 l2 and l1 oh you can tell no what's the
difference but again there are a hundred thousand a
hundred thousand uh not entirely sure but in the point the
point is that in the l1 in the l1 you have so many more weights
a cluster at the zero but there are a few larger weights
in the l2 you have all the weights are pretty
small can you see right there is no large weights
so l1 doesn't shrink the weight l1 just get them
towards zero okay that's why you had this big guy here
boom okay um finally i know i'm over time
the last notebook which is the one that is computing the uncertainty
uh through user usage of the dropout right so kernel execute all
uh where is it run all [Music]
so what are we doing here how do we compute the uncertainty
in the previous uh in the in the in the previous
uh in the previous lesson right in the slides i just showed you
so here we have some points i try to fit them
with my network and you get something like this
can you tell me what network i used what is the
uh where is the chat can you tell what is the
non-linearity i used you should know right
you don't answer answer okay um and so here yeah
and then here i show you how this uncertainty looks okay so what is
this this i'm using the uh the network with
the dropout and then i actually don't use the evaluation mode i just use the
training mode such that the dropout is still on and
then i compute the variance of the predictions of the network by
sending multiple times the data through okay so here you have
range in hundred you know i just provide 100
times my data inside the network okay so this
is a network with the ReLU let me show you how a network with it
hyperbolic dungeon works so oh yeah
let me kill this one so here i create the network
and this is the network train with the hyperbolic tangent
such it's much nicer right and then i show you
the network is in train mode right but then i i feed
several times i feed 100 times my data points
inside and then i evaluate the mean you can see now
that the network mean the network outputs a uncertainty which is constant
even if you move outside this interval which was the region where the
training data were coming so you can see now that
these uncertainty estimation are a bit you know funky
as in different activation functions give you different kind of estimation
they are not even calibrated nevertheless you have the uncertainty
close to the data points it's very very very tiny right so you
can tell how far you are from the training region and we use this
this trick here this this this part in order to
so again this variance here is like it's a it's a
differentiable function and so you can run gradient descent
right in this in order to minimize the variance
and this would allow you to move towards the region
where the uh where the uh data points where
basically the the training region this this is what we use for the
our policy right in our uh driving scenario
so oh that was it right uh we reached the end
of the class the end of the semester uh it was such a great honor to be
your teacher for this semester i screw up a little bit maybe halfway
through thank you for you know helping me
getting back uh on my feet uh
if you need anything right really anything just let me know i
i'm always open to discuss and help out and
explain and again as i told you before we can even think
to have one more extra lesson in a month time if you want
the same way zoom and whatever uh we about the energy based models um
again if you have any question about all any of the lessons you can
write on youtube in the comments below i will answer
if you have like specific uh if you are interested in making
drawings and visualization uh you can always
actually should talk to me because i'm actually uh
creating a group for visualizing machine learning stuff
um and we have the website we have plenty of things to do english has to be
fixed in many of the uh in many of the of the of the
contributions some math is broken and you know there is plenty of
things uh open source things to do if you are
inclined if you are interested and and yeah i think pretty much that's it
um i i'll see you next monday right again you should submit the three video
presentation i made a um i made a tutorial about how to make a
presentation if you like how i teach and you may want to hear my opinion about
how you should present your work uh it's on again on youtube
and yeah i think that's it all right so again thank you so much and
i can't wait to see all your results for the
for for the project um [Music]
see you on monday good luck bye about the class ah [ __ ] there was one
more notebook damn okay
okay let me ah okay i can't go over i'm too late right in the extra and there is
one more notebook i wanted to talk about which is the
so this is the projection notebook yeah okay so
ah okay maybe we can do an extra lesson with the projection uh and i talk about
this next week up to you guys more questions i know i
it's late and uh there was this notebook it's
okay yeah you know i want to be teaching more
okay no no question there is a question google uses
visor to select either parameters for its neural for
its networks those tend to be either random search or gaussian process for
hyper parameter optimize exactly uh yeah but i haven't worked like i
haven't tried them out so i can't really give you a opinion so i
i know they exist but i'm not i don't exactly know everything yet
okay uh i think that's it right okay so see you monday thanks yeah
of course boy post a lasagna oh i put the i put the lemon
cake right keep the teaching going yeah
that's for sure i think we are there Yann is teaching
also in the in the fall actually Yann and KyungHyun are pairing up
and they are teaching in the fall and i will be also teaching the labs
but i don't know we haven't yet discussed the content
i'm like oh boy more teaching but it's fun
but okay bye
[Music] okay so i think
that was it for today unless there are some questions for me
for jan uh i know you send me emails i have
a few i think a few hundred emails from you
i will answer uh i will answer don't worry uh don't don't
don't worry too much we can figure out what's happening right don't don't freak
out as i told you before we can have an
extra lesson in one month for the energy based models uh whenever
i'm done preparing it uh again this is like up to
you voluntary it's not it's completely off
class right it's like i was thinking that it makes sense since
someone asked to create like a lab for the energy based
model and i said yes well i i always keep my word so uh i didn't
manage to do it on time but you know i will do i will work for this
um questions nope all right so it was has been an
honor uh seriously i i loved being uh been teaching
to you this semester uh you had so many questions and
especially when we switched to this online format
i think i personally loved it right so at least in my opinion before we had jan
lecturing and maybe you are a bit shy uh i'm not shy i mean i i don't care
so i i think this format where you write questions and i just read out whatever
uh it's in your mind uh it really worked well in terms of
you know figuring out what are those aspects that are at least
a little bit uh harder to uh to to to to catch right uh because again we
we may not be able to figure out what is the part that is
less um less clear maybe because we've been talking about
these things for a while now so again i think if you write those
questions i read them and we have like a speaker we have like
some kind of conversation presentation it's much more effective in
terms of content and delivery right yeah i want
to echo what alfredo said it was a it was a pleasure teaching the class as
well you know despite the circumstances and uh um you know i'm very thankful to
alfredo i think you know he's putting his heart into
this as you can tell and um and and
you know i'm i'm i'm really i'm really thankful for for him to do all this job
um because i think it uh it makes a huge difference in terms of the
uh usefulness of the class and um so thank you alfredo
thank you and Jiachen right Jiachen made the whole the challenge
actually did a huge amount oh my god this last month
that's the biggest competition possible to put together the data
the basic code the data loader uh this was i mean he worked on this for
you know a lot for the last few months and and then you
know gathering gathering all the other results so thank
you Jiachen i think it's been two months now
he's been working on this stuff all right guys
thank you you always get me uh you know just tweet me
i answer every time uh uh anything you need you know you can find me my door
is always open uh or in the office or here on on zoom right so
as alfredo said this this project uh we have this uh autonomous driving project
and uh you know uh we need all the help we can get with this so if you
are in some of the top teams and you are interested in participating uh
get in touch with alfredo and you know you could
work on this during the summer or or perhaps beyond
all right all right um goodbye guys all right okay bye bye guys